welcome to meditating with John rebecky
I'm a cognitive psychologist and a
cognitive scientist at the University of
Toronto where I academically teach and
scientifically study phenomena like
mindfulness related phenomena like
Insight flow mystical experience
transformative experience higher states
of consciousness the cultivation of
wisdom and the aspiration to
enlightenment I've been practicing the
past the meditation meta contemplation
Tai Chi Chuan and Qigong as an
integrated ecology of practices for for
29 years and teaching and professionally
for close to 20 years welcome for
joining us for the first time you are
welcome but please understand that this
is a progressive course the introductory
course is done and every alternative
Monday is a dharma day in which I teach
now an advanced technique a principle of
practice that builds on previous
principles and practices to catch up go
to the links in this description and you
can find all the previous lessons and
you can catch up with us and then join
us when you see fit so today we are
going to sit as I said alternative
Monday's our Dharma days the remaining
Tuesdays through Fridays our sit days
sometimes do a review I'm going to do
review again today I'm not going to do
an extensive review of the content of
the Patna subluxated you know I get that
yesterday if you want to check that
review you can check the descriptions
both in Monday and the video and also
yesterday's to get reviewed about the
practice but I'm going to do it again
with you so we get one more time of it
being exemplified to you and so that's
what the plan is we will do a sit
together we will go through Lexi o
Divina and then I will take questions we
have a little bit more time on Wednesday
although we've lost some time but
hopefully everything will still work out
smoothly please remember to like this
dream to increase the visibility in the
YouTube algorithm that will help me to
help as many people as possible for the
questions please limit the questions to
the ecology of practices within this
course and we will give priority today
to questions specifically about Lexi o
Divina
right I think that's everything I think
everything is stabilized now odd
opportunity right odd activities but
it's about so please get yourself in
your posture set your phones to do not
disturb we will sit press slightly
shorter time to make up for some of the
lost time and to give us a little bit of
space for lectio divina so we're going
to sit for just 12 minutes this time
we're gonna sit for just 12 minutes so
please get ready and we will begin when
I say begin begin
slowly begin to come out of your
practice trying his best years you can
to integrate with your cultivated in
your practice with your everyday
consciousness and cognition
perhaps by reciting the five promises to
yourself
all right let's do some Luxio davina
together so let's start with the sacred
prose again this is the enlightened
heart and anthology of sacred poetry
sorry it's sacred we'll start with a
sacred poetry enlightened heart an
anthology of sacred poetry edited by
Steven Mitchell excellent translator
this is a poem by Rilke of course it's
translated from the German nevertheless
even in translation I think it'll still
sing to you so enacted engagement I set
my intention coming into you a state I'm
intending for reverence and I'm reading
for transformation ah not to be cut off
not through the slightest partition shut
up shut out from the law of the stars
the inner what is it if not intensified
sky hurled through with birds and deep
with the winds of homecoming so what
calls out to me many times that I read
this different things call out to me and
his poem today it's calling out to me is
hurled through with birds and deep with
the winds of homecoming intensified sky
the Internet's sense of right I'm
picking up an association and I'm
imagining Oh a huge open sky Birds
moving through it and they they they
they be they speak they exemplify the
openness the affordance of the sky
hurled through with Birds but the winds
of homecoming there's a remembering
there's a coming home it's I can only
get an inkling of it but there's this
sense of when I connect to that in
earnest there's an expansiveness but
there's a remembering there's a
homecoming
and getting an inkling for associations
a sense of what that's like and there's
something calling to me that at the
beginning of the poem now not to be cut
off that longing to be deeply deeply
connected to the inner aspect of things
the depths of things but it's also a
remembering coming home what would it be
like if that perspective that state of
being and seeing in comprehensive for me
way of life a connectedness at
homecoming that sense of the inner
things intensified sky hurled through
words would that be like what would I be
seeing what would be disclosed to me
will be demanded from me how would I
need to transform to conform to what's
being realized how would it come into
continuity of contact or right
relationship with this yes yes
the sacred pros the enlightened part an
anthology of steak repose edited by
Steven Mitchell this is from father he's
a Jewish middle play tennis from around
the time of Christ
I mean he's considered by many people
the first actual theologian today and
it's in quotes because he's referring to
the word today means boundless and
inexhaustible eternity periods of months
and years and of time in general our
ideas of men who calculate by number but
the true name of turnit II is today
boundless and inexhaustible so we call
someone immediately is the the shared
fiction that it's Wednesday that somehow
there's Wednesday around me but of
course there's no Wednesday this is a
Odin's day before we have the Norse
interaction with the NORs we didn't even
have the term and we didn't even cut up
time like that and we were
hunter-gatherers we didn't even have the
calendar then a Wednesday that doesn't
mean there's no time in the sense of
presencing and can you sense it the
inexhaustible Ness
the boundlessness here right now always
and that always but it's not a static
always it's a right it's the today the
hereness nowness right that boundless
inexhaustible but not static always
that's the true name of eternity how
appropriate for the fourth stage of
lectio right when we're trying to
realize the ecstatic eternal so I come
into this come into this I'm already
doing it I'm already it's picking up on
the terms the inexhaustible the
boundless I'm already seeing this I mean
acting and I'm doing it with you I just
did it and then is with that realization
that just came sometimes it does that
comes spontaneously you don't even have
to go through sort of explicitly the
stages they just unfold for you I get
that sense what he's talking about of it
that the true name of eternity is today
but not that today of a Wednesday but
the today that was just disclosed to me
what would it be like to live in the
face of that disclosure comprehensively
sati always remembering it but that
demand from me what I need to constantly
remember how could I conform more to
this but what what is needed what is
calling to me how do I come into more of
a conformity with Eternity is the always
but not static inexhaustible boundless
today and how are those two now talking
to each other
the cyntha matter ah to not be cut off
the inner sky the Eternity that they're
they're talking to each other they're
singing to each other form like it's
palpable it's a presence
and a sense of gratitude I took place
that I couldn't get to on my own I got
to a place because of the logos what
would of the texts gratitude for that
gratefulness but I commit myself to
remembering throughout the day these
realizations to realize them the
connectedness to the inner intensified
sky the homecoming but also the today
that is eternity all right so let's take
a few questions on that truth what if
what is salient is darker sad are you
avoiding this or going deeply into this
as well go deeply into it if the
emotional Association is sad or the
starlit there's something that needs to
speak if it resonates with you there is
something that needs to be seen there
there's something that needs to speak
there's an insight that needs to occur
you're not if this is not about feeling
good this is about feeling real those
right ultimately those are the same but
that requires a deep change in what we
mean by good but it doesn't mean
comfortable but it means the right
relationship to what is most real
that's what enjoyment used to mean joy
isn't pleasure to N join it being in and
joy might be in that connectedness to
what really matters and is most real so
in that sense yes you should if what
leaves out is dark what is needing to be
spoken
what is the insight what you need to see
that you're not seeing Ronnie Chan how
to avoid interruption of my meditation
because of my own excitement for the for
the feeling of thought absence Oh
sorry no normally I can give sort of
like here is what you do yeah I know
what you're talking about just keep
doing it and so you have to some you
have to get to the place where the
novelty of the thoughtless space isn't
so well isn't so novel and you can only
you can only deal with novelty through
repetition retirement I'm sorry I wish I
could tell you some thing you can do but
for this I'm you know and we I know what
you're talking about went through it and
everybody does and you just have to get
to a place where right you it loses that
novelty now here's the thing there's a
bit of it there is a bit of a thing that
you have to pay attention to right that
it shouldn't lose its importance because
it loses the salience of novelty it
should become salient to not because
it's novel and it's jumping out and you
get all excited but because you're
internalizing it you're taking it to
heart you're weaving it into the very
fabric of your consciousness and your
sense of self
harima high chroma I believe you were on
the discord server on Monday thank you
for that
do we need to read chapters in order for
instance in Shaw's book on I am Lucas I
would I wouldn't read I mean if you're
going to use it as your sacred prose and
I think maybe that's what you mean I
would read the book first through you
have to read something you have to first
get something in formatively that's like
a platform if this is talked about and
they're all over this tux I'm like do
davina you have like the literal reading
you have to get the you have to be you
have to get the informative meaning and
that's a platform for the transformative
reading so I would make sure you
understood Shaw you've read it back to
front I think you props you have you've
got that thing and then you can't read
it as you intuitively see fit okay these
are Carly
during the past and is that okay to use
mantra or imagery like a white bubble
around to help or is that not a part of
the practice so as I've said before like
legally as a mentor it's in out
can you symmetry but here's the thing
are you looking through the image at the
movement of your breath
are you listening through the mantra to
the sensations of your breath or are you
looking at the mantra and at the image
if the images are a lens that help you
focus
if the mantra is a lens that help you
focus use it but if you are just looking
at the mantra or the image and starting
to play with the mantra itself or the
image itself then it is an impediment to
the practice raaaah
yonas in the project practice when
applying nota I'm usually imagining a
person or landscape or a creature while
exhaling doesn't that work against my
thought pattern and practice while
inhaling so that's that's that's part of
the inner coach thing and eventually
what you want to do is can you shift off
the product that's anchoring the
movement of mind it's what you're doing
is you're imagining a landscape to
expand then that's good this is and
everybody has to start this way remember
we've talked repeatedly about the inner
coach the ralph but what you want to do
can you get to the sense of expanding
without having to anchor it to any
particular image or if anything a very
very very vague and diffuse image that
you're looking through like I was just
talking about and so you want to move to
it and when you get just that sense of
the opening of the heart which is I
think the original meaning of opening
the heart I don't think it means feeling
wonderful thoughts towards people as
I've argued but when you get that
opening then that is perfectly consonant
with the movement of the pasta towards
the still center mark Lefevre as always
I'm grateful for Mark's presence both
here the discord server Maura enlivens
the community that he belongs to it's a
great gift it's a great virtue ecstatic
eternal is this the practice of our
participating a New Ager to lean a
relationship are we building cognitive
flexibility through the imaginal psychic
technology exactly that's exactly right
that's exactly what's happening you are
doing a kind of insight at the level
you're doing a restructuring and insight
at the level of your participatory
knowing
the agents of Rena relationship and for
those of you who don't quite know what
marks talking about he's talking about
ideas that are developed in the video
series awakening from the meaning crisis
or in the discussion series voices with
verve Iggy pura Kroger declare fire an
earlier answer are you saying that you
should have read the pose all the way
through first and understood it you
should be yes you should have like I
don't mean I don't mean every time you
practice but yeah very good
so don't pay the piece of prose you have
not met before informatively if you have
read it sometime before informatively so
you've got the information because if
you don't your paint it will and should
we try hora t2 gathering the information
and you will limit the cognitive space
the cognitive mode available to you
though you can take heart for the
transformation process so you should
have read it maybe so right maybe more
than
or informatively then immediately pick
it up and read it transformative so you
should have some familiarity with the
informative content of the prose or
poetry before you then take it into
Lexia so i've been told that my good
friend guys sense talk is here I love
guy he's an amazing friend and you know
one of these greatly one of these
companions on the on the road on the way
on the path of the logos that just
affords you moving for dinner and
appreciate an understanding on the
journey and steps so I'm very grateful
for the relationship that I have
forgotten for without brings to this
world I had an excellent deal logos with
guy last night is going to come out of
his channel that's gonna come out on my
channel I'm just just wonderful just
wonderful you want an example of a big
deal oh this is and when it's going I
think that's one of the great of that
discussion we had last night that the
focus really is at the cutting agent the
work the tea and I important and Chris
Peter
we're all working on so so diligently so
thank you guys for your presence I want
to thank all of you for your presence
this was you know we it was a lot of
leap you know a lot of bugling and a lot
of coping and a lot of adaptive
flexibility and you know great just you
know so thank you oh one more question
Karima up there should you have read the
poetry also yes
same thing poetry shouldn't be
absolutely de novo to you so as i said
thank you everybody
q everybody for being here wonderful
sangha if you know you know the real
thing you know Spinoza talks about real
things they're rare in the sense of you
know they're difficult and because
they're rare and they're rarity and that
it's the quality of their like they go
beyond our expectations but ways that we
didn't expect they are the unexpectedly
unexpected and that's a sign of their
realness and what's happening with that
saying
has exactly that beauty so thank you for
that I want to as always thank my dear
friend and techno measum are always
there always solving problems behind the
scene so that this can happen and of
course also for the help my beloved son
Jett Jason is always here also coping
and managing things instant you that
need to be done please subscribe to the
channel notify the next deal the final
ends of the lecture series that I've
mentioned awakening meaning practice and
do the discussion voices with Verve AP I
mentioned the one that's going to come
out and rise channel and the voices
Wilbur Vicki yeah where all these things
are like explored and they're developed
in F and you can situate this practice
within a much more in comprehensive a
way of life invite others who might
benefit to participation this series as
always I strongly or MN you know
pleasure of that Brett is here it was on
there on Monday beautiful if you can
there's links in the description go to
the discord server there's people who
have done this sitting right as a
practice and are they're ready to talk
about it there's a community whose wants
to situate this in a broader project of
cultivating wisdom awakening from the
meeting crisis so there there's it's
it's there go there for you it's
beautiful a reminder that we are doing
this every weekday morning at 9:30
Eastern Time a reminder the continuity
of practice more important than quantity
of practice there is no enemy worse than
your own mind and body no Ally no true
friend no to true companion on the way
greater than your own mind and body as
the Buddha said be lamps unto yourself
I'll see you all tomorrow
take good care bye-bye